<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:id="L1916_1911">
 <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Circular letter from Micheál Ó Duibhguin, November 1915</title>
                
                <author>Micheál Ó Duibhguin</author>
                
                <editor></editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <p/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <address>
                        <name>An Foras Feasa</name>
                        <orgName>Maynooth University</orgName>
                        <postBox>Co. Kildare</postBox>
                        <placeName>
                            <country>IRE</country>
                            <settlement>Maynooth</settlement>
                        </placeName>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <idno n="L1916_1911"/>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>All rights reserved. No part of this image may be reproduced, distributed, or
        transmitted in any form or by any means, including photocopying, recording, or other
        electronic or mechanical methods, without the prior written permission of the institutional
        or private owner of the image and the Letters of 1916 project. For permission requests,
        write to the Letters of 1916 at letters1916@gmail.com. </p>
                    <p>Copyright  2015, Letters of 1916, Maynooth</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <!-- Series statement ?-->
                <p>PUT A STATEMENT</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="summary">
                    
                        <p>A typed circular letter signed by Micheál Ó Duibhguin, Secretary of Cumann na bPíobairí, requesting financial contributions for the family of Brigid Kenny (d. 1915), known as the &#39;Queen of Irish Fiddlers&#39;. Kenny had been a musician but due to prolonged illness and funeral expenses  her family were left in debt.  Ó Duibhguin also mentions that Kenny&#39;s daughter, Christine, &#39;has inherited much of her mother&#39;s talent and we hope she will not be forgotten when concert, ceillidhs, etc. are being organised’.</p>
                    
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>Allen Library</repository>
                        
                        <idno type="collection">Allen Library, Br. Allen Collection: IE/AL/1915/23</idno><!-- NOT ALWAYS -->
                    	
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
           </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                
            	  
				<correspAction type="sending">
					 
                    <persName>Micheál Ó Duibhguin</persName>
                    
                     
                    <placeName>41 Parnell Square, Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
                    
                    
                    <date when="1915-11">1915-11</date>
                    
            	</correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- Type of the letter should be separate -->
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                    
                        <item n="gender">Male</item><!--put an IF -->
                        
                        <item n="assigned_category">Art and literature</item>
                    
                    	
                        	<item n="tag">Family life</item>
                    	
                        	<item n="tag">Children</item>
                    	
                        	<item n="tag">Art and literature</item>
                    	
                           
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-EN">English</language>
            </langUsage>
	 </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <ab>SAMPLE: This electronic transcription was created as part of the crowdsourced project
                    Letters of 1916: creating history.
            </ab>
        </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:17.615965" who="#PythonScript_pageDublicatesResolve">
                Old page dublicate removed
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:48.306516" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesTransform">
                New Letter created
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 15:55:03.253236" who="#PythonScript">
                Filtered from Completed List
            </change>
        
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<!-- problem of images...<facsimile> 
        <graphic />
</facsimile> -->

   
    <text type="letter"><!-- issue to resolve with a previous process? -->
        <body>
           
                <pb n="4795" facs="f7a6831b833308e03a57321784e25520.jpg"/>
                <!-- (TOP LEFT ) --> Established 17th February, 1900.<lb/> President - Edward Martyn ESQ. <lb/> Union Pipes and War Pipes Taught. <lb/> Information supplied as to Pipes and Pipers. <lb/> Letters requiring immediate attention may <lb/> be addressed to the Secretary at <!-- ( END ) --> <!-- (TOP RIGHT) --> </address> Cumann na  bPíobairí, <lb/> 41 PARNELL SQUARE, DUBLIN, <lb/> </date> November 1915.<lb/> </salute> A Chara, <lb/> you are no doubt aware of the death of Mrs Brigid <lb/> Kenny, the "Queen of Irish Fiddlers" on the 7th <del>inst</del> ult. She had <lb/> been seriously unwell for over twelve months previously and had to <lb/> refuse all engagements. Her illness was, consequently, a source <lb/> of heavy expense to her family and with the additional burden of <lb/> the funeral charges now upon them they find themselves in debt. <lb/> They feel this very much as all who know them will understand.<lb/> But I think that the late Mrs. Kenny's friends and admirers have <lb/> merely to know of the fact in order to save her relatives any <lb/> worry of the kind. The Pipers Club are therefore undertaking a <lb/> small collection and I shall gladly receive and acknowledge any <lb/> sums that may be sent me. </p> Students and collectors of Irish music are under debt <lb/> to the Kenny family which no mere money offering can repay. It <lb/> is no exaggeration to say that they and their connections have <lb/> kept Irish instrumental music alive in Dublin. Members of the <lb/> Feis Ceoil Association will know of the valuable collections of <lb/> unpublished airs furnished by Mr. and Mrs. Kenny. </p> Mrs. Kenny's daughter, Christine, has inherited much of <lb/> her mother's talent and we hope that she will not be forgotten <lb/> when concerts, ceilidhs, etc.. are being organised. Her ad&#x2014; <lb/> dress is 5 Madden's Court, Thomas Street.<lb/> Is  mise, <lb/> Le mór meas, <lb/> Micheál Ó Duibhguin <lb/> Rúnaine<lb/> <!-- ( END OF PAGE ) --> Please address any reply <lb/> to me at:&#x2014;<lb/> <address>5 David Road, Glasnevin</address>.
           
        </body>
    </text>
     

</TEI>


    