<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:id="L1916_213">
 <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Patrick Langford Beazley to Piaras Béaslaí to Piaras on submitting an article on the Irish Language, 17 February 1916</title>
                
                <author>Patrick Langford Beazley</author>
                
                <editor></editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <p/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <address>
                        <name>An Foras Feasa</name>
                        <orgName>Maynooth University</orgName>
                        <postBox>Co. Kildare</postBox>
                        <placeName>
                            <country>IRE</country>
                            <settlement>Maynooth</settlement>
                        </placeName>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <idno n="L1916_213"/>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>All rights reserved. No part of this image may be reproduced, distributed, or
        transmitted in any form or by any means, including photocopying, recording, or other
        electronic or mechanical methods, without the prior written permission of the institutional
        or private owner of the image and the Letters of 1916 project. For permission requests,
        write to the Letters of 1916 at letters1916@gmail.com. </p>
                    <p>Copyright  2015, Letters of 1916, Maynooth</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <!-- Series statement ?-->
                <p>PUT A STATEMENT</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="summary">
                    
                        <p>Piaras&#39;s father discusses Piaras submitting an article under a pseudonym on the Irish language for the St. Patrick&#39;s day edition of an unnamed newspaper. He suggests that Piaras should mention the fact that Irish was the language St. Patrick used.</p>
                    
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>National Library of Ireland</repository>
                        
                        <idno type="collection">Piaras Béaslaí Papers, Collection List 44, MS 33,972 / 11</idno><!-- NOT ALWAYS -->
                    	
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
           </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                
				<correspAction type="receiving">
				
            		<persName>Piaras Béaslaí</persName>
            	
            	  
				<correspAction type="sending">
					 
                    <persName>Patrick Langford Beazley</persName>
                    
                     
                    <placeName>Cheshire, England</placeName>
                    
                    
                    <date when="1916-02-17">1916-02-17</date>
                    
            	</correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- Type of the letter should be separate -->
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                    
                        <item n="gender">Male</item><!--put an IF -->
                        
                        <item n="assigned_category">Art and literature</item>
                    
                    	
                        	<item n="tag">Art and literature</item>
                    	
                           
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-EN">English</language>
            </langUsage>
	 </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <ab>SAMPLE: This electronic transcription was created as part of the crowdsourced project
                    Letters of 1916: creating history.
            </ab>
        </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:07.988847" who="#PythonScript_pageDublicatesResolve">
                Old page dublicate removed
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:47.847234" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesTransform">
                New Letter created
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:48.623553" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesResolve">
                Additional page merged into Letter
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:48.961218" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesResolve">
                Additional page merged into Letter
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 15:55:03.280014" who="#PythonScript">
                Filtered from Completed List
            </change>
        
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<!-- problem of images...<facsimile> 
        <graphic />
</facsimile> -->

   
    <text type="letter"><!-- issue to resolve with a previous process? -->
        <body>
           
                <pb n="526" facs="03a9ae73fa7b77ded8559be284629500.jpg"/>
                <address>"GLENGARIFF"<lb/>
RUDGRAVE SQUARE,<lb/>
EGREMONT,<lb/>
CHESHIRE.</address>

<date>17<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> Feb., 1916.</date>
<salute>My dearest Pierce,</salute>
<p>I just lost the post in<lb/>writing this letter. I find I<lb/>cannot now catch the 8 o'clock<lb/>post, which would bring this<lb/>letter to you in the morning,<lb/>but you ought to have it<lb/>to&#x2014;morrow evening. About<lb/>that article, which you sug&#x2014;<lb/>gested for next week. I can&#x2014;<lb/>not take one for next week<lb/>because I have one, and had<lb/>it when I got your letter in<lb/>hand for next week, and<lb/>I have received for consider&#x2014;<lb/>ation two others or so to which<pb/>
           
                <pb n="527" facs="9f2073b728adc1852d72b76d0978521c.jpg"/>
                I am more or less committed.<lb/> The position, as I explained to you,<lb/> is rather delicate and diffi&#x2014;<lb/>cult for me. You would have<lb/> to use a pseudonym be&#x2014;<lb/>cause it would not do to<lb/> let people think I was writ&#x2014;<lb/>ing the articles myself or<lb/> favoring my son by giving<lb/> prominence to his writings<lb/> &#x2014; one or other of which that they<lb/> would be sure to think if<lb/> you wrote under your name.<lb/> But with a good pseudonym<lb/> &#x2014; the name, as it were, of<lb/> some living person &#x2014; I might<lb/> be able to get in an occas&#x2014;<lb/>ional article. They would have<lb/> to be good and appropriate so<lb/> that no obligation could be<lb/> raised on that score, and not<pb/> more than about a column in<lb/> length, that is, about fourteen or<lb/> fifteen hundred words. I would<lb/> suggest that you should send<lb/> me <hi rend="underline">by Monday, March 2</hi> &#x2014; nothing<lb/> can be done for next week<lb/> as I have indicated &#x2014; an article<lb/> for <hi rend="underline">the issue of March 10</hi>, in<lb/> preparation for St. Patrick's Day,<lb/> showing how desirable it is<lb/> that <hi rend="underline"> with English</hi>the Irish peo&#x2014;<lb/>ple should grip the language<lb/> <del>as well as</del> St. Patrick used as<lb/> well as the faith he preached<lb/> so successfully in Ireland. It <lb/>seems to me that the subject is a<lb/> charming one and might be<lb/> made a great deal of by pointing<lb/> out some of the beautiful re&#x2014;<lb/>ligious expressions in the old<lb/> tongue (giving only the English<lb/> translation, except in two<lb/> or three particular cases, per&#x2014;<lb/>haps, to <del>give</del> <add>impart</add> a tone to the article),<pb/>
           
                <pb n="528" facs="ac4e299fa4e9948adfe35f047802c864.jpg"/>
                explaining how the old tongue<lb/> was associated with the most<lb/> flourishing periods of the faith<lb/> in Ireland, how it is, as it were<lb/>, turned round the old ruin s &#x2014;<lb/> the ruins of chapels and wells &#x2014;<lb/> towers whose bring it to<lb/> mind, and dwelling on the con&#x2014;<lb/>trast between the cold secular<lb/> spirit indicated by the language<lb/> of ordinary social life in English<lb/> speaking lands and the brotherly,<lb/> Christian warmth conveyed in<lb/> Irish in the language of social inter&#x2014;<lb/>course. Make your sentences<lb/> fairly crisp and let yourself go.<lb/> If you throw in some strengthen<lb/>ing< figures in the middle or so,<lb/> so much the better. I have an<lb/> article on St. Patrick (to which I am<lb/> committed) for the issue of <hi rend="underline">March 17</hi>,<lb/> but it does not touch on this.<lb/> Don't forget to choose a name. If you<lb/> think of a good heading so much the better.</p>
<p>You will have had mother's letter.<lb/> Don't forget to write <hi rend="underline">very soon again</hi><lb/> if you want another such letter.<lb/> We are well thank God. I dont know<lb/> yet what affect the shortening of paper supplies<lb/> will have on the C.T.</p> <salute>With fond love form mother,<lb/> Ever affectionately</salute> Father.
           
        </body>
    </text>
     

</TEI>


    