<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:id="L1916_246">
 <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Michael Collins to James Ryan, 23 August 1916</title>
                
                <author>Michael Collins</author>
                
                <editor></editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <p/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <address>
                        <name>An Foras Feasa</name>
                        <orgName>Maynooth University</orgName>
                        <postBox>Co. Kildare</postBox>
                        <placeName>
                            <country>IRE</country>
                            <settlement>Maynooth</settlement>
                        </placeName>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <idno n="L1916_246"/>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>All rights reserved. No part of this image may be reproduced, distributed, or
        transmitted in any form or by any means, including photocopying, recording, or other
        electronic or mechanical methods, without the prior written permission of the institutional
        or private owner of the image and the Letters of 1916 project. For permission requests,
        write to the Letters of 1916 at letters1916@gmail.com. </p>
                    <p>Copyright  2015, Letters of 1916, Maynooth</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <!-- Series statement ?-->
                <p>PUT A STATEMENT</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="summary">
                    
                        <p>James Ryan (1891-1970) studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
                    
                        <p>Michael Collins (1890-1922) served as aide-de-camp to Joseph Plunkett in the GPO during the Rising and was imprisoned in Frongach. He went on to become Minister for Finance in the First Dáil, IRA Director of Information and President of the Provisional Government.</p>
                    
                        <p>The letter was written to Ryan from Frongach internment camp. Ryan had already been released and Collins fills him on changes in the camp and the conditions and morale of his fellow prisoners.</p>
                    
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>University College Dublin Archives</repository>
                        
                        <idno type="collection">Dr James Ryan Papers, P 88/34</idno><!-- NOT ALWAYS -->
                    	
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
           </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                
				<correspAction type="receiving">
				
            		<persName>James Ryan</persName>
            	
            	  
				<correspAction type="sending">
					 
                    <persName>Michael Collins</persName>
                    
                     
                    <placeName>Frongach internment camp, Bala, Wales</placeName>
                    
                    
                    <date when="1916-08-23">1916-08-23</date>
                    
            	</correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- Type of the letter should be separate -->
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                    
                        <item n="gender">Male</item><!--put an IF -->
                        
                        <item n="assigned_category">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
                    
                    	
                        	<item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
                    	
                           
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-EN">English</language>
            </langUsage>
	 </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <ab>SAMPLE: This electronic transcription was created as part of the crowdsourced project
                    Letters of 1916: creating history.
            </ab>
        </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:08.424045" who="#PythonScript_pageDublicatesResolve">
                Old page dublicate removed
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:08.424880" who="#PythonScript_pageDublicatesResolve">
                Old page dublicate removed
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:48.298866" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesTransform">
                New Letter created
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:48.560521" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesResolve">
                Additional page merged into Letter
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 15:55:03.265837" who="#PythonScript">
                Filtered from Completed List
            </change>
        
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<!-- problem of images...<facsimile> 
        <graphic />
</facsimile> -->

   
    <text type="letter"><!-- issue to resolve with a previous process? -->
        <body>
           
                <pb n="630" facs="14228bcf2740541af4c2b2918c2cbd8a.jpg"/>
                <address>Frongoch<lb/>
Bala</address> <date>23/8/16</date>

<salute>My Dear Jim</salute>
<p>I got your card today and the<lb/> letter some weeks ago. Was very pleased<lb/> indeed to hear from you &amp; so were all the<lb/> gang. Possibly you have heard from one<lb/> or other of the 'returns' that we were all trans<lb/>ferred from the huts to the lower station where<lb/> they used to make whiskey. Most of us do<lb/> not appreciate the change as much as we<lb/> ought to. But there are many consolations<lb/> all the same. The officers down here take<lb/> themselves very seriously &amp; insist on trying to<lb/> do things on a strict military basis. Honestly<lb/> its most amusing at times but I cannot<lb/> mention the incidents. They wouldn't be good<lb/> for the censor and then I couldn't do them<lb/> justice by reason of the restriction writing<lb/> places on ones language. Now that there<lb/> seems to be some certainty as to the definiteness<lb/> of our stay, things are falling into more<lb/> organized channels. It has become possible<lb/> to do a little reading &amp; study.  Cards have<lb/> lost their glamour since your departure<lb/> (<hi rend="underline">you</hi> can take this how <add>you</add> like) but there is a<lb/> chess tournament for those who play, that<lb/> seems to be worse. They make the hell of<lb/> a row over it. You can hear Dick saying<pb/>
           
                <pb n="631" facs="718f666e754845a063258317ddfb0ad3.jpg"/>
                <hi rend="underline">magnificent</hi> play on my part: a few weeks<lb/> ago also we had a sports meeting. a great day<lb/> high tea for the prize winners afterwards<lb/> It consisted of such things as tinned pears jam<lb/> &amp; pudding. We gorged ourselves &amp; ended up<lb/> with a concert, going home late. I hear that<lb/> most of the men who have gone home are still<lb/> unemployed &#x2014; is that so? If it is, some of them<lb/> would be as well off here &#x2014; that is in a way.<lb/> What do you thing of things yourself? I mustn't<lb/> say anything as so many of my letters have<lb/> been returned lately! Old Dan is here<lb/> still &#x2014; he doesn't seem to be in such good<lb/> form as <del>was when</del> he used to. I think he<lb/> is rather disappointed at his continued <lb/>detention, so too are others, although generally<lb/> that feeling appears to be wearing off, and<lb/> some of them are no longer gloomy when<lb/> they are told that the first couple of winters will<lb/> be the worst.  It is good of you to think<lb/> about that cake. We are eagerly looking forward<lb/> to its arrival, and Mort says that he'll eat any<lb/>&#x2014;thing you send. Of course he may not<lb/> have an opportunity as we are no longer at<lb/> the next table to them. Doras damned in a<lb/> most whole&#x2014;hearted manner when I showed<lb/> him your card. The early rising has sent him<lb/> be damned entirely. When you see May<lb/> do not fail to give her my regards or any<lb/> addition you think suitable. Of course you<lb/> can explain to any of your friends about the<lb/> two letters weekly. Have you recovered from<lb/> the weddings yet? There were numerous speculations as<lb/> to how must have been enjoying yourself on the occasions.</p>
<salute>Best wishes from self &amp; all the <unclear>C.</unclear></salute>
Mick Collins
           
        </body>
    </text>
     

</TEI>


    