<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:id="L1916_247">
 <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Michael Collins to James Ryan, 2 September 1916</title>
                
                <author>Michael Collins</author>
                
                <editor></editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <p/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <address>
                        <name>An Foras Feasa</name>
                        <orgName>Maynooth University</orgName>
                        <postBox>Co. Kildare</postBox>
                        <placeName>
                            <country>IRE</country>
                            <settlement>Maynooth</settlement>
                        </placeName>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <idno n="L1916_247"/>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>All rights reserved. No part of this image may be reproduced, distributed, or
        transmitted in any form or by any means, including photocopying, recording, or other
        electronic or mechanical methods, without the prior written permission of the institutional
        or private owner of the image and the Letters of 1916 project. For permission requests,
        write to the Letters of 1916 at letters1916@gmail.com. </p>
                    <p>Copyright  2015, Letters of 1916, Maynooth</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <!-- Series statement ?-->
                <p>PUT A STATEMENT</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="summary">
                    
                        <p>James Ryan (1891-1970) studied medicine in UCD. He was appointed chief medical officer in the GPO during the Easter Rising. After the Rising he was imprisoned in Stafford and, later, Frongoch and was released in August 1916. Ryan was later a founder member of Fianna Fáil and a government minister.</p>
                    
                        <p>Michael Collins (1890-1922) served as aide-de-camp to Joseph Plunkett in the GPO during the Rising and was imprisoned in Frongach. He went on to become Minister for Finance in the First Dáil, IRA Director of Information and President of the Provisional Government.</p>
                    
                        <p>The letter is written from Frongach internment camp. Ryan had been imprisoned there with Collins but released early. Collins fills Ryan in on some of the happenings in the camp but mentions that many of his letters had &#39;meeting with accidents&#39;: they had not passed the censor&#39;s office. The letter also subtly refers to political organisation in the camp and tells Ryan to keep an eye on developments in Dublin Corporation.</p>
                    
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>University College Dublin Archvies</repository>
                        
                        <idno type="collection">Dr James Ryan Papers, P 88/35</idno><!-- NOT ALWAYS -->
                    	
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
           </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                
				<correspAction type="receiving">
				
            		<persName>James Ryan</persName>
            	
            	  
				<correspAction type="sending">
					 
                    <persName>Michael Collins</persName>
                    
                     
                    <placeName>Frongach internment camp, Bala, Wales</placeName>
                    
                    
                    <date when="1916-09-02">1916-09-02</date>
                    
            	</correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- Type of the letter should be separate -->
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                    
                        <item n="gender">Male</item><!--put an IF -->
                        
                        <item n="assigned_category">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
                    
                    	
                        	<item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
                    	
                        	<item n="tag">politics</item>
                    	
                           
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-EN">English</language>
            </langUsage>
	 </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <ab>SAMPLE: This electronic transcription was created as part of the crowdsourced project
                    Letters of 1916: creating history.
            </ab>
        </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:08.455553" who="#PythonScript_pageDublicatesResolve">
                Old page dublicate removed
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:08.456736" who="#PythonScript_pageDublicatesResolve">
                Old page dublicate removed
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:47.806270" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesTransform">
                New Letter created
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:48.898993" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesResolve">
                Additional page merged into Letter
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 15:55:03.310020" who="#PythonScript">
                Filtered from Completed List
            </change>
        
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<!-- problem of images...<facsimile> 
        <graphic />
</facsimile> -->

   
    <text type="letter"><!-- issue to resolve with a previous process? -->
        <body>
           
                <pb n="632" facs="1b472a238345d421fe3100eb364077b2.jpg"/>
                <note>What do<lb/> you think<lb/> of those<lb/> articles by<lb/> my judge.They're &#x2014; <lb/>we all say. M.</note>
<!-- Above lines written sideways across top left of page just above the salute -->

Same Kip,<lb/> <date>Monday 2nd.</date>
<salute>My Dear Jim</salute>
<p>Of course its ever so long<lb/> since I got your last letter &amp; that<lb/> excellent cake &#x2014; which came in<lb/> perfect form. The old tables as you<lb/> knew them no longer exist but that<lb/> didn't hinder me from sharing your<lb/> cake with Colm DD George &amp; Morkan.<lb/> They all enjoyed it and thought you were<lb/> still a packet. It isn't my fault that<lb/> I haven't acknowledged it long ago<lb/> but most of my letters have been<lb/> meeting with accidents &#x2014; <foreign>a' dtuigeann tú?</foreign><lb/> I saw your letter to little Mr Dore about<lb/> the weddings & your fortune at nap<lb/> &#x2014; was wondering if the explanation<lb/> was your superior staying power &#x2014;<lb/> very likely it was so that your<pb/>
           
                <pb n="633" facs="c222d2060f14ca3686084261ff247ab2.jpg"/>
                winning was just taking it from them.<lb/> I only hope that they didn't borrow it back<lb/> like some others who need not<lb/> be mentioned. Things go on in<lb/> much the same way here, but there<lb/> have been some interesting happenings<lb/> lately, which the Censor's Department forbids<lb/> us to speak about. Even so the<lb/> Dublin Corporation meeting tomorrow will<lb/> give you some idea. Your old friends<lb/> continue to keep well &#x2014; as I am writing this<lb/> I hear some one say "good play on your<lb/> part" &#x2014; and I wonder why it seemed<lb/> so funny to us, and Daly <del>wh</del>with his<lb/> I'm nothing &#x2014; honestly. I'm addressing<lb/> this to your town house as very likely you'll<lb/> be back there by this time. Hope your lip<lb/> is alright - there were some doubts about<lb/> the accuracy of the description of the ailment.</p>
<p>If you see May Gray don't fail to give her<lb/> my kindest regards whatever you may feel like<lb/> yourself. Even if you're not able to send<lb/> another cake for some time I hope you'll<lb/> write anyway.</p> <salute>Goodbye. Yours sincerely</salute> Michael
           
        </body>
    </text>
     

</TEI>


    