<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:id="L1916_429">
 <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from Gerald O&#39;Driscoll to his father Denis, 24 May 1916</title>
                
                <author>Gerald O&#39;Driscoll</author>
                
                <editor></editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <p/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <address>
                        <name>An Foras Feasa</name>
                        <orgName>Maynooth University</orgName>
                        <postBox>Co. Kildare</postBox>
                        <placeName>
                            <country>IRE</country>
                            <settlement>Maynooth</settlement>
                        </placeName>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <idno n="L1916_429"/>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>All rights reserved. No part of this image may be reproduced, distributed, or
        transmitted in any form or by any means, including photocopying, recording, or other
        electronic or mechanical methods, without the prior written permission of the institutional
        or private owner of the image and the Letters of 1916 project. For permission requests,
        write to the Letters of 1916 at letters1916@gmail.com. </p>
                    <p>Copyright  2015, Letters of 1916, Maynooth</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <!-- Series statement ?-->
                <p>PUT A STATEMENT</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="summary">
                    
                        <p>Gerald O&#39;Dricoll (d. 1946) was in the British Navy and this letter, to his father, was written from H.M.S.Temeraire.  In the letter he describes his shock at the &#39;rebellion in Dublin&#39; and refers to the reaction of he and his fellow soldiers at the front to the Rising, noting that &#39;our fellow country-men at the front felt it all the more keenly&#39;. His reaction is typical of many Irish soldiers in the British army; he laments the destruction of Sackville Street (O&#39;Connell Street) and refers to one of the rebels as a &#39;half-demented, crazy, misguided fool&#39;. He also writes about family matters and an annual boxing tournament.</p>
                    
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>Denis McGrath, private collection</repository>
                        
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
           </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                
				<correspAction type="receiving">
				
            		<persName>Denis O&#39;Driscoll</persName>
            	
            	
                    <placeName>Dublin, Ireland</placeName>
                
                <!-- <date>WE DON'T HAVE A DEVOTED FIELD!!!</date> -->
                </correspAction>
                  
				<correspAction type="sending">
					 
                    <persName>Gerald O&#39;Driscoll</persName>
                    
                     
                    <placeName>H.M.S. Temeraire, Grand Fleet</placeName>
                    
                    
                    <date when="1916-05-24">1916-05-24</date>
                    
            	</correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- Type of the letter should be separate -->
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                    
                        <item n="gender">Male</item><!--put an IF -->
                        
                        <item n="assigned_category">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
                    
                    	
                        	<item n="tag">Easter Rising Ireland 1916</item>
                    	
                           
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-EN">English</language>
            </langUsage>
	 </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <ab>SAMPLE: This electronic transcription was created as part of the crowdsourced project
                    Letters of 1916: creating history.
            </ab>
        </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:09.732353" who="#PythonScript_pageDublicatesResolve">
                Old page dublicate removed
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:47.769907" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesTransform">
                New Letter created
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:48.636047" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesResolve">
                Additional page merged into Letter
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 15:55:03.455877" who="#PythonScript">
                Filtered from Completed List
            </change>
        
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<!-- problem of images...<facsimile> 
        <graphic />
</facsimile> -->

   
    <text type="letter"><!-- issue to resolve with a previous process? -->
        <body>
           
                <pb n="1137" facs="7fcf9749625d690e9f52b319b43ca735.jpg"/>
                <note>Must be 1916</note>
<address>H.M.S. Temeraire,<lb/>
Grand Fleet,<lb/>
c/o G.P.O. London</address>
<date>24/5/6</date>

<salute>My dear Father,</salute>
<p>In a letter from Maggie I was very<lb/> pleased to learn of Finneen's arrival home and also<lb/> to be assured of his general health &amp; fitness. I have<lb/> not replied to Maggie yet as for some time past I<lb/> have been too busy altogether. I was of course <lb/>shocked by the Dublin rebellion and indeed not a<lb/> little anxious for the safety of those near and dear to<lb/> me. I was worried and restless. The possibility of<lb/> Maggie &amp; Barbara being in the danger zone, and this<lb/> coupled with the temporary stoppage of mails &amp;<lb/> communication of every description increased my<lb/> solicitude. But I will not waste time in dogmatising<lb/> on such madness; we and our fellow countrymen at<lb/> the front felt it all the more keenly. It would<lb/> seem as if the temple of glory built by our brave<lb/> Irish regiments, had been pulled down by their<lb/> own kindred. In a paper that Maggie sent me<lb/> I notice the name <add>&amp; address</add> of Dot's brother as one of<lb/> the rebels deported. I wonder what his ow<lb/>n brother Jack will say when he hears the news at<lb/> the front. That half-demented, crazy, misguided<pb/>
           
                <pb n="1138" facs="7d3307fc9f788a6381b46591c67b06af.jpg"/>
                fool Willie Halpin is also one of them. Patriotism!<lb/> My God! and he knows as much about Irish<lb/> History as a Fiji cannibal. The outcome of it <lb/>was death and sorrow, and the destruction of the<lb/> finest and statliest street in Europe; &#x2014; a street<lb/> that every Dublin <hi rend="underline">man</hi>, <hi rend="underline">must</hi> have been justly proud.</p>
<p>Things up here are very much the same, as far as I<lb/> am at liberty to disclose. In order to relieve the tenor of<lb/> a <add><del>ratl</del> rather</add> multifarious routine, the annual boxing tournament took<lb/> place recently; a sort of inter&#x2014;ship for the championship<lb/> of the squadron. Our friend Bob Hanley <del>took</del> won the<lb/> lightweight championship of our own particular squadron after<lb/> four fights. It appeared to me to be an easy thing for<lb/> him. He is a skilful and clean fighter, a hard hitter,<lb/> and I have little doubt that he will win the championship<lb/> of the Grand Fleet <hi rend="underline">should that competition</hi> ever come off.</p>
<p>I had a field service post card this morning from<lb/> Finneen in which I am assured that he is quite well.</p>
<p>I was not aware that he <del>was</del> is a full corporal but<lb/> was certainly not surprised. I passed a preliminary exam<lb/> recently with a fairly decent margin of marks. I am the more<lb/> elated because I was totally unprepared for such. It in no way<lb/> embraced <add>the</add> category of my present study. The latter is varied<lb/> and complicated but I have every confidence for the ultimate<lb/> result. That is all. It is late and I am for duty. Adieu for<lb/> the present with love to Mother and Babs.</p> <salute>Your affectionate Son,</salute> <hi rend="underline">Gerald</hi>
           
        </body>
    </text>
     

</TEI>


    