<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:id="L1916_636">
 <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Letter from James Finn to May Fay, 27 January 1916</title>
                
                <author>James Finn</author>
                
                <editor></editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <p/>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>
                    <address>
                        <name>An Foras Feasa</name>
                        <orgName>Maynooth University</orgName>
                        <postBox>Co. Kildare</postBox>
                        <placeName>
                            <country>IRE</country>
                            <settlement>Maynooth</settlement>
                        </placeName>
                    </address>
                </publisher>
                <idno n="L1916_636"/>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>All rights reserved. No part of this image may be reproduced, distributed, or
        transmitted in any form or by any means, including photocopying, recording, or other
        electronic or mechanical methods, without the prior written permission of the institutional
        or private owner of the image and the Letters of 1916 project. For permission requests,
        write to the Letters of 1916 at letters1916@gmail.com. </p>
                    <p>Copyright  2015, Letters of 1916, Maynooth</p>
                </availability>
                <date when="2015">2015</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <!-- Series statement ?-->
                <p>PUT A STATEMENT</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="summary">
                    
                        <p>This is from a series of letters written between James Finn and his fiancée Mary (May) Fay. They became engaged in January 1916 and married in June. They were not to be married long as in 1919 he fell ill with the great flu epidemic, it led to heart damage and he died in 1922 as she was expecting their fourth child. She held on to his letters as her reminder of him. </p>
                    
                        <p></p>
                    
                        <p>James Finn (1877 - 1922) was a civil servant, working in the National Health Service Commission on Mount Street. Family history says that he was advising on the restructuring of the civil service as part of setting up the new government in 1922 and that eminent figures in that project were visiting him in his sick bed so that they could consult with him. Neither May nor James were politically active, although like many in the Civil Service, learned Irish. One can sense their shifting sympathies in the letters.</p>
                    
                        <p></p>
                    
                        <p>The letter mainly concerns arrangements for May&#39;s impending visit and references to local gossip.</p>
                    
                </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <repository>Finn Family Collection</repository>
                        
                    </msIdentifier>
                </msDesc>
           </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
            <correspDesc>
                
				<correspAction type="receiving">
				
            		<persName>May Fay</persName>
            	
            	
                    <placeName>Togherstown, Westmeath, Ireland</placeName>
                
                <!-- <date>WE DON'T HAVE A DEVOTED FIELD!!!</date> -->
                </correspAction>
                  
				<correspAction type="sending">
					 
                    <persName>James Finn</persName>
                    
                     
                    <placeName>Rathmines, Dublin</placeName>
                    
                    
                    <date when="1916-01-27">1916-01-27</date>
                    
            	</correspAction>
            </correspDesc>
            <textClass>
                <!-- Type of the letter should be separate -->
                <keywords>
                    <list>
                    
                        <item n="gender">Male</item><!--put an IF -->
                        
                        <item n="assigned_category">Love letters</item>
                    
                    	
                        	<item n="tag">Love letters</item>
                    	
                           
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en-EN">English</language>
            </langUsage>
	 </profileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <samplingDecl>
            <ab>SAMPLE: This electronic transcription was created as part of the crowdsourced project
                    Letters of 1916: creating history.
            </ab>
        </samplingDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:10.769856" who="#PythonScript_pageDublicatesResolve">
                Old page dublicate removed
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:48.388077" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesTransform">
                New Letter created
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 14:33:48.658941" who="#PythonScript_mergeLetterPagesResolve">
                Additional page merged into Letter
            </change>
        
            <change when="2015-08-11 15:55:03.422869" who="#PythonScript">
                Filtered from Completed List
            </change>
        
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<!-- problem of images...<facsimile> 
        <graphic />
</facsimile> -->

   
    <text type="letter"><!-- issue to resolve with a previous process? -->
        <body>
           
                <pb n="1544" facs="4550eefd6f8dec1454311f4955060c24.jpg"/>
                <date>27 Jan, 1916.</date>

<salute>My darling girl,</salute>
<p>This is going to be a very short <lb/>
note indeed.  Glad to see from your letter today <lb/>
that mumps are better and that we may <lb/>
really hope to see you both on Saturday.  If <lb/>
you are coming by first train <hi rend="underline">let me know</hi> <lb/>
as I should like to meet you at station <lb/>
shall be on tenderhooks until then.  By the <lb/>
way wasn't a bit hurt over Miss Gertie Kelly's <lb/>
remarks about the dancers.  I suppose you'll <lb/>
see the marriage in Dublin next week if you <lb/>
care to turn up at Church.  Where is it to be <lb/>
and is Father McNamee going to pull the bolt. <lb/>
If they're looking for a cheap job they ought to go <lb/>
to the Registry Office as John threatened he would. <lb/>
Remember me to your mother and Mrs S.</p>
<salute>Your loving little man<lb/>
James</salute>
           
                <pb n="1584" facs="49acc036fd451a0e731a6978ea140dfe.jpg"/>
                <p>If USED FOR TRANSMISSION TO ANY PLACE ABROAD TO WHICH THE 1d. RATE<lb/> OF LETTER POSTAGE DOES NOT APPLY, THE ADDITIONAL POSTAGE REQUIRED<lb/> SHOULD BE PREPARED BY MEANS OF ADHESIVE POSTAGE STAMPS.</p>
<!-- Upsidedown on image -->

Miss Fay
<address>Togherstown<lb/>
Ballina<lb/>
<hi rend="underline">Mullingar</hi></address>
           
        </body>
    </text>
     

</TEI>


    